Finding Aid for Albert Robinson Crittenden papers, 1868-1933
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Albert Robinson Crittenden papers 1868-1933
Crittenden, Albert Robinson, 1867-1933.
2 linear feet
851039 Aa 2
Professor of Classics at Olivet College and University of Michigan. Correspondence, lecture notes, unpublished manuscripts, account books; and two manuscripts by Lisla Crittenden.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by V.V. Crittenden (donor no. 542 ) in 1938.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Born in 1867, Albert Robinson Crittenden graduated from Ann Arbor High School in 1887. After teaching in the public schools for two years he entered the University of Michigan receiving his bachelor's degree in 1874. He was a high school principal in Ypsilanti, Michigan and Moline, Illinois. During these years up to 1900, Crittenden came to be recognized as an outstanding teacher of Latin in the secondary schools. In order to gain a better background for his work he spent the year 1900-1901 at the American Academy in Rome. During his stay in Rome he married Lisla A. van Valkenburg, a fellow student at the Academy. After his year abroad he returned to the University of Michigan for graduate study, receiving his master's degree in 1902. From then until 1909 Crittenden was Professor of Latin at Olivet College, working in the meantime for his doctorate, which he received in 1908. While on leave from Olivet in 1908-9 he began teaching at the University of Michigan as a substitute for Professor Walter Dennison, who was then in Rome. Beginning as an instructor he rose to the rank of Assistant Professor in 1910, to Associate Professor in 1916, and finally to Professor in 1924. He died on December 17, 1933.
The Crittenden collection consists of correspondence, lecture notes for classes taught and classes taken. There are also student materials of his wife Lisla Van Valkenburg Crittenden. Correspondence includes letters from Robert C. Angell, C. H. Crittenden, Ernest Crittenden, Lisla Crittenden, Walter Dennison, Joseph H. Drake, John R. Effinger, Washington Gardner, Benjamin L. D'Ooge, Martin L. D'Ooge, Francis W. Kelsey, Moritz Levi, Albert H. Pattengill, and Allen S. Whitney.
Subjects:
Civilization, Classical--Study and teaching--Michigan.; Frankfort (Mich.); Classical philology--Study and teaching--Michigan.; Olivet College.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Classical Studies.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Greek.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. School of Education.
Contributors:
Angell, Robert Cooley, 1899-; Crittenden, C. H.; Crittenden, Ernest.; Crittenden, Lisla Van Valkenburg.; Dennison, Walter, 1869-1917.; D'Ooge, Benjamin L. (Benjamin Leonard), b. 1860.; D'Ooge, Martin Luther, 1839-1915.; Drake, Joseph H. (Joseph Horace), 1860-1947.; Effinger, John R. (John Robert), 1869-1933.; Gardner, Washington, 1845-1928.; Kelsey, Francis W. (Francis Willey), 1858-1927.; Levi, Moritz, b. 1857; Pattengill, Albert Henderson, 1842-1906.; Whitney, Allen Sisson, 1857-1944.
- Correspondence, undated and 1868-1933
  - Undated, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - 1868-1881 (Box 1)
  - 1882-1885 (Box 1)
  - 1886 (Box 1)
  - 1887-1888 (Box 1)
  - 1889-1890 (Box 1)
  - January-August 1891 (Box 1)
  - September 1891-June 1892 (Box 1)
  - July 1892-August 1893 (Box 1)
  - September 1893-March 1894 (Box 1)
  - April-December 1894 (Box 1)
  - 1895-1896 (Box 1)
    (letter from Washington Gardner, February 27, 1895)
  - 1897-1898 (Box 1)
  - 1899 (Box 1)
  - January-June 1900 (Box 1)
  - July 1900-December 1901 (Box 1)
  - January-June 1902 (Box 1)
  - July 1902-December 1903 (Box 1)
  - 1904 (Box 1)
    (includes letter from Walter Dennison, April 23, 1904)
  - 1905 (Box 1)
    (includes letter from Moritz Levi, December 22, 1905)
  - January-May 1906 (Box 1)
  - June 1906-February 1907 (Box 1)
    (includes letter of Allen S. Whitney, February 6, 1907)
  - March-December 1907 (Box 1)
  - 1908 (Box 1)
  - 1909-1919 (Box 1)
  - 1920-October 1930 (Box 1)
  - November 1930-October 1931 (Box 1)
  - November 1931-1933 (Box 1)
- Lecture Notes for Classes
  - Greek philosophy (Box 1)
  - Latin, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Latin papers and lectures (Box 1)
  - Roman history (Box 2)
  - Roman history lecture notes, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Rome (Box 2)
- Other materials
  - Teacher's certificate papers (Box 2)
    (includes reports of Committee on the Revision of the Requirements for Admission, Graduation, and Certification)
  - Miscellaneous papers (Box 2)
    (includes report on methods of increasing intellectual interest of students at University of Michigan by Robert C. Angell)
  - Cards, programs, pictures, advertisements, etc., 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Olivet College (Box 2)
  - Course notebooks, 10 volumes (Box 2)
  - Lisla Van Valkenburg Crittenden class materials, 1 folder and 25 volumes (Box 2)